morning, “that you have ordered a good dinner to-day, because I have reason to expect an
addition to our family party.”
“Who do you mean, my dear?
I know of nobody that is coming, I am sure, unless Charlotte Lucas should happen to call
in; and I hope my dinners are good enough for her.
I do not believe she often sees such at home.”
“The person of whom I speak is a gentleman and a stranger.”
Mrs. Bennet’s eyes sparkled.
“A gentleman and a stranger!
It is Mr. Bingley, I am sure.
Why, Jane—you never dropped a word of this—you sly thing!
Well, I am sure I shall be extremely glad to see Mr. Bingley.
But—good Lord!
how unlucky!
there is not a bit of fish to be got to-day.
Lydia, my love, ring the bell.
I must speak to Hill this moment.”
“It is not Mr. Bingley,” said her husband; “it is a person whom I never saw in the
whole course of my life.”
This roused a general astonishment; and he had the pleasure of being eagerly questioned
by his wife and five daughters at once.
After amusing himself some time with their curiosity, he thus explained:—“About a
month ago I received this letter, and about a fortnight ago I answered it; for I thought
it a case of some delicacy, and requiring early attention.
It is from my cousin, Mr. Collins, who, when I am dead, may turn you all out of this house
as soon as he pleases.”
“Oh, my dear,” cried his wife, “I cannot bear to hear that mentioned.
Pray do not talk of that odious man.
I do think it is the hardest thing in the world, that your estate should be entailed
away from your own children; and I am sure, if I had been you, I should have tried long
ago to do something or other about it.”
Jane and Elizabeth attempted to explain to her the nature of an entail.
They had often attempted it before: but it was a subject on which Mrs. Bennet was beyond
the reach of reason; and she continued to rail bitterly against the cruelty of settling
an estate away from a family of five daughters, in favour of a man whom nobody cared anything
about.
“It certainly is a most iniquitous affair,” said Mr. Bennet; “and nothing can clear
Mr. Collins from the guilt of inheriting Longbourn.
But if you will listen to his letter, you may, perhaps, be a little softened by his
manner of expressing himself.”
“No, that I am sure I shall not: and I think it was very impertinent of him to write to
you at all, and very hypocritical.
I hate such false friends.
Why could not he keep on quarrelling with you, as his father did before him?”
“Why, indeed, he does seem to have had some filial scruples on that head, as you will
hear.”
“Hunsford, near Westerham, Kent, 15th October.
“Dear Sir, “The disagreement subsisting between yourself
and my late honoured father always gave me much uneasiness; and, since I have had the
misfortune to lose him, I have frequently wished to heal the breach: but, for some time,
I was kept back by my own doubts, fearing lest it might seem disrespectful to his memory
for me to be on good terms with anyone with whom it had always pleased him to be at variance.”—‘There,
Mrs. Bennet.’—“My mind, however, is now made up on the subject; for, having received
ordination at Easter, I have been so fortunate as to be distinguished by the patronage of
the Right Honourable Lady Catherine de Bourgh, widow of Sir Lewis de Bourgh, whose bounty
and beneficence has preferred me to the valuable rectory of this parish, where it shall be
my earnest endeavour to demean myself with grateful respect towards her Ladyship, and
be ever ready to perform those rites and ceremonies which are instituted by the Church of England.
As a clergyman, moreover, I feel it my duty to promote and establish the blessing of peace
in all families within the reach of my influence; and on these grounds I flatter myself that
my present overtures of good-will are highly commendable, and that the circumstance of
my being next in the entail of Longbourn estate will be kindly overlooked on your side, and
not lead you to reject the offered olive branch.
I cannot be otherwise than concerned at being the means of injuring your amiable daughters,
and beg leave to apologize for it, as well as to assure you of my readiness to make them
every possible amends; but of this hereafter.
If you should have no objection to receive me into your house, I propose myself the satisfaction
of waiting on you and your family, Monday, November 18th, by four o’clock, and shall
probably trespass on your hospitality till the Saturday se’nnight following, which
I can do without any inconvenience, as Lady Catherine is far from objecting to my occasional
absence on a Sunday, provided that some other clergyman is engaged to do the duty of the
day.
I remain, dear sir, with respectful compliments to your lady and daughters, your well-wisher
and friend, “William Collins.”
“At four o’clock, therefore, we may expect this peace-making gentleman,” said Mr. Bennet,
as he folded up the letter.
“He seems to be a most conscientious and polite young man, upon my word; and, I doubt
not, will prove a valuable acquaintance, especially if Lady Catherine should be so indulgent as
to let him come to us again.”
“There is some sense in what he says about the girls, however; and, if he is disposed
to make them any amends, I shall not be the person to discourage him.”
“Though it is difficult,” said Jane, “to guess in what way he can mean to make us the
atonement he thinks our due, the wish is certainly to his credit.”
Elizabeth was chiefly struck with his extraordinary deference for Lady Catherine, and his kind
intention of christening, marrying, and burying his parishioners whenever it were required.
“He must be an oddity, I think,” said she.
“I cannot make him out.
There is something very pompous in his style.
And what can he mean by apologizing for being next in the entail?
We cannot suppose he would help it, if he could.
Can he be a sensible man, sir?”
“No, my dear; I think not.
I have great hopes of finding him quite the reverse.
There is a mixture of servility and self-importance in his letter which promises well.
I am impatient to see him.”
“In point of composition,” said Mary, “his letter does not seem defective.
The idea of the olive branch perhaps is not wholly new, yet I think it is well expressed.”
To Catherine and Lydia neither the letter nor its writer were in any degree interesting.
It was next to impossible that their cousin should come in a scarlet coat, and it was
now some weeks since they had received pleasure from the society of a man in any other colour.
As for their mother, Mr. Collins’s letter had done away much of her ill-will, and she
was preparing to see him with a degree of composure which astonished her husband and
daughters.
Mr. Collins was punctual to his time, and was received with great politeness by the
whole family.
Mr. Bennet indeed said little; but the ladies were ready enough to talk, and Mr. Collins
seemed neither in need of encouragement, nor inclined to be silent himself.
He was a tall, heavy-looking young man of five-and-twenty.
His air was grave and stately, and his manners were very formal.
He had not been long seated before he complimented Mrs. Bennet on having so fine a family of
daughters, said he had heard much of their beauty, but that, in this instance, fame had
fallen short of the truth; and added, that he did not doubt her seeing them all in due
time well disposed of in marriage.
This gallantry was not much to the taste of some of his hearers; but Mrs. Bennet, who
quarrelled with no compliments, answered most readily,—
“You are very kind, sir, I am sure; and I wish with all my heart it may prove so;
for else they will be destitute enough.
Things are settled so oddly.”
“You allude, perhaps, to the entail of this estate.”
“Ah, sir, I do indeed.
It is a grievous affair to my poor girls, you must confess.
Not that I mean to find fault with you, for such things, I know, are all chance in this
world.
There is no knowing how estates will go when once they come to be entailed.”
“I am very sensible, madam, of the hardship to my fair cousins, and could say much on
the subject, but that I am cautious of appearing forward and precipitate.
But I can assure the young ladies that I come prepared to admire them.
At present I will not say more, but, perhaps, when we are better acquainted——”
He was interrupted by a summons to dinner; and the girls smiled on each other.
They were not the only objects of Mr. Collins’s admiration.
The hall, the dining-room, and all its furniture, were examined and praised; and his commendation
of everything would have touched Mrs. Bennet’s heart, but for the mortifying supposition
of his viewing it all as his own future property.
The dinner, too, in its turn, was highly admired; and he begged to know to which of his fair
cousins the excellence of its cookery was owing.
But here he was set right by Mrs. Bennet, who assured him, with some asperity, that
they were very well able to keep a good cook, and that her daughters had nothing to do in
the kitchen.
He begged pardon for having displeased her.
In a softened tone she declared herself not at all offended; but he continued to apologize
for about a quarter of an hour.
CHAPTER XIV
DURING dinner, Mr. Bennet scarcely spoke at all; but when the servants were withdrawn,
he thought it time to have some conversation with his guest, and therefore started a subject
in which he expected him to shine, by observing that he seemed very fortunate in his patroness.
Lady Catherine de Bourgh’s attention to his wishes, and consideration for his comfort,
appeared very remarkable.
Mr. Bennet could not have chosen better.
Mr. Collins was eloquent in her praise.
The subject elevated him to more than usual solemnity of manner; and with a most important
aspect he protested that he had never in his life witnessed such behaviour in a person
of rank—such affability and condescension, as he had himself experienced from Lady Catherine.
She had been graciously pleased to approve of both the discourses which he had already
had the honour of preaching before her.
She had also asked him twice to dine at Rosings, and had sent for him only the Saturday before,
to make up her pool of quadrille in the evening.
Lady Catherine was reckoned proud by many people, he knew, but he had never seen anything
but affability in her.
She had always spoken to him as she would to any other gentleman; she made not the smallest
objection to his joining in the society of the neighbourhood, nor to his leaving his
parish occasionally for a week or two to visit his relations.
She had even condescended to advise him to marry as soon as he could, provided he chose
with discretion; and had once paid him a visit in his humble parsonage, where she had perfectly
approved all the alterations he had been making, and had even vouchsafed to suggest some herself,—some
shelves in the closets upstairs.
“That is all very proper and civil, I am sure,” said Mrs. Bennet, “and I dare say
she is a very agreeable woman.
It is a pity that great ladies in general are not more like her.
Does she live near you, sir?”
“The garden in which stands my humble abode is separated only by a lane from Rosings Park,
her Ladyship’s residence.”
“I think you said she was a widow, sir? has she any family?”
“She has one only daughter, the heiress of Rosings, and of very extensive property.”
“Ah,” cried Mrs. Bennet, shaking her head, “then she is better off than many girls.
And what sort of young lady is she?
Is she handsome?”
“She is a most charming young lady, indeed.
Lady Catherine herself says that, in point of true beauty, Miss de Bourgh is far superior
to the handsomest of her sex; because there is that in her features which marks the young
woman of distinguished birth.
She is unfortunately of a sickly constitution, which has prevented her making that progress
in many accomplishments which she could not otherwise have failed of, as I am informed
by the lady who superintended her education, and who still resides with them.
But she is perfectly amiable, and often condescends to drive by my humble abode in her little
phaeton and ponies.”
“Has she been presented?
I do not remember her name among the ladies at court.”
“Her indifferent state of health unhappily prevents her being in town; and by that means,
as I told Lady Catherine myself one day, has deprived the British Court of its brightest
ornament.
Her Ladyship seemed pleased with the idea; and you may imagine that I am happy on every
occasion to offer those little delicate compliments which are always acceptable to ladies.
I have more than once observed to Lady Catherine, that her charming daughter seemed born to
be a duchess; and that the most elevated rank, instead of giving her consequence, would be
adorned by her.
These are the kind of little things which please her Ladyship, and it is a sort of attention
which I conceive myself peculiarly bound to pay.”
“You judge very properly,” said Mr. Bennet; “and it is happy for you that you possess
the talent of flattering with delicacy.
May I ask whether these pleasing attentions proceed from the impulse of the moment, or
are the result of previous study?”
“They arise chiefly from what is passing at the time; and though I sometimes amuse
myself with suggesting and arranging such little elegant compliments as may be adapted
to ordinary occasions, I always wish to give them as unstudied an air as possible.”
Mr. Bennet’s expectations were fully answered.
His cousin was as absurd as he had hoped; and he listened to him with the keenest enjoyment,
maintaining at the same time the most resolute composure of countenance, and, except in an
occasional glance at Elizabeth, requiring no partner in his pleasure.
By tea-time, however, the dose had been enough, and Mr. Bennet was glad to take his guest
into the drawing-room again, and when tea was over, glad to invite him
“Protested that he never read novels” H.T Feb 94
to read aloud to the ladies.
Mr. Collins readily assented, and a book was produced; but on beholding it (for everything
announced it to be from a circulating library) he started back, and, begging pardon, protested
that he never read novels.
Kitty stared at him, and Lydia exclaimed.
Other books were produced, and after some deliberation he chose “Fordyce’s Sermons.”
Lydia gaped as he opened the volume; and before he had, with very monotonous solemnity, read
three pages, she interrupted him with,— “Do you know, mamma, that my uncle Philips
talks of turning away Richard?
and if he does, Colonel Forster will hire him.
My aunt told me so herself on Saturday.
I shall walk to Meryton to-morrow to hear more about it, and to ask when Mr. Denny comes
back from town.”
Lydia was bid by her two eldest sisters to hold her tongue; but Mr. Collins, much offended,
laid aside his book, and said,— “I have often observed how little young
ladies are interested by books of a serious stamp, though written solely for their benefit.
It amazes me, I confess; for certainly there can be nothing so advantageous to them as
instruction.
But I will no longer importune my young cousin.”
Then, turning to Mr. Bennet, he offered himself as his antagonist at backgammon.
Mr. Bennet accepted the challenge, observing that he acted very wisely in leaving the girls
to their own trifling amusements.
Mrs. Bennet and her daughters apologized most civilly for Lydia’s interruption, and promised
that it should not occur again, if he would resume his book; but Mr. Collins, after assuring
them that he bore his young cousin no ill-will, and should never resent her behaviour as any
affront, seated himself at another table with Mr. Bennet, and prepared for backgammon.
CHAPTER XV.
MR.
COLLINS was not a sensible man, and the deficiency of nature had been but little assisted by
education or society; the greatest part of his life having been spent under the guidance
of an illiterate and miserly father; and though he belonged to one of the universities, he
had merely kept the necessary terms without forming at it any useful acquaintance.
The subjection in which his father had brought him up had given him originally great humility
of manner; but it was now a good deal counteracted by the self-conceit of a weak head, living
in retirement, and the consequential feelings of early and unexpected prosperity.
A fortunate chance had recommended him to Lady Catherine de Bourgh when the living of
Hunsford was vacant; and the respect which he felt for her high rank, and his veneration
for her as his patroness, mingling with a very good opinion of himself, of his authority
as a clergyman, and his right as a rector, made him altogether a mixture of pride and
obsequiousness, self-importance and humility.
Having now a good house and a very sufficient income, he intended to marry; and in seeking
a reconciliation with the Longbourn family he had a wife in view, as he meant to choose
one of the daughters, if he found them as handsome and amiable as they were represented
by common report.
This was his plan of amends—of atonement—for inheriting their father’s estate; and he
thought it an excellent one, full of eligibility and suitableness, and excessively generous
and disinterested on his own part.
His plan did not vary on seeing them.
Miss Bennet’s lovely face confirmed his views, and established all his strictest notions
of what was due to seniority; and for the first evening she was his settled choice.
The next morning, however, made an alteration; for in a quarter of an hour’s tête-à-tête
with Mrs. Bennet before breakfast, a conversation beginning with his parsonage-house, and leading
naturally to the avowal of his hopes, that a mistress for it might be found at Longbourn,
produced from her, amid very complaisant smiles and general encouragement, a caution against
the very Jane he had fixed on.
“As to her younger daughters, she could not take upon her to say—she could not positively
answer—but she did not know of any prepossession;—her eldest daughter she must just mention—she
felt it incumbent on her to hint, was likely to be very soon engaged.”
Mr. Collins had only to change from Jane to Elizabeth—and it was soon done—done while
Mrs. Bennet was stirring the fire.
Elizabeth, equally next to Jane in birth and beauty, succeeded her of course.
Mrs. Bennet treasured up the hint, and trusted that she might soon have two daughters married;
and the man whom she could not bear to speak of the day before, was now high in her good
graces.
Lydia’s intention of walking to Meryton was not forgotten: every sister except Mary
agreed to go with her; and Mr. Collins was to attend them, at the request of Mr. Bennet,
who was most anxious to get rid of him, and have his library to himself; for thither Mr.
Collins had followed him after breakfast, and there he would continue, nominally engaged
with one of the largest folios in the collection, but really talking to Mr. Bennet, with little
cessation, of his house and garden at Hunsford.
Such doings discomposed Mr. Bennet exceedingly.
In his library he had been always sure of leisure and tranquillity; and though prepared,
as he told Elizabeth, to meet with folly and conceit in every other room in the house,
he was used to be free from them there: his civility, therefore, was most prompt in inviting
Mr. Collins to join his daughters in their walk; and Mr. Collins, being in fact much
better fitted for a walker than a reader, was extremely well pleased to close his large
book, and go.
In pompous nothings on his side, and civil assents on that of his cousins, their time
passed till they entered Meryton.
The attention of the younger ones was then no longer to be gained by him.
Their eyes were immediately wandering up the street in quest of the officers, and nothing
less than a very smart bonnet, indeed, or a really new muslin in a shop window, could
recall them.
But the attention of every lady was soon caught by a young man, whom they had never seen before,
of most gentlemanlike appearance, walking with an officer on the other side of the way.
The officer was the very Mr. Denny concerning whose return from London Lydia came to inquire,
and he bowed as they passed.
All were struck with the stranger’s air, all wondered who he could be; and Kitty and
Lydia, determined if possible to find out, led the way across the street, under pretence
of wanting something in an opposite shop, and fortunately had just gained the pavement,
when the two gentlemen, turning back, had reached the same spot.
Mr. Denny addressed them directly, and entreated permission to introduce his friend, Mr. Wickham,
who had returned with him the day before from town, and, he was happy to say, had accepted
a commission in their corps.
This was exactly as it should be; for the young man wanted only regimentals to make
him completely charming.
His appearance was greatly in his favour: he had all the best parts of beauty, a fine
countenance, a good figure, and very pleasing address.
The introduction was followed up on his side by a happy readiness of conversation—a readiness
at the same time perfectly correct and unassuming; and the whole party were still standing and
talking together very agreeably, when the sound of horses drew their notice, and Darcy
and Bingley were seen riding down the street.
On distinguishing the ladies of the group the two gentlemen came directly towards them,
and began the usual civilities.
Bingley was the principal spokesman, and Miss Bennet the principal object.
He was then, he said, on his way to Longbourn on purpose to inquire after her.
Mr. Darcy corroborated it with a bow, and was beginning to determine not to fix his
eyes on Elizabeth, when they were suddenly arrested by the sight of the stranger; and
Elizabeth happening to see the countenance of both as they looked at each other, was
all astonishment at the effect of the meeting.
Both changed colour, one looked white, the other red.
Mr. Wickham, after a few moments, touched his hat—a salutation which Mr. Darcy just
deigned to return.
What could be the meaning of it?
It was impossible to imagine; it was impossible not to long to know.
In another minute Mr. Bingley, but without seeming to have noticed what passed, took
leave and rode on with his friend.
Mr. Denny and Mr. Wickham walked with the young ladies to the door of Mr. Philips’s
house, and then made their bows, in spite of Miss Lydia’s pressing entreaties that
they would come in, and even in spite of Mrs. Philips’s throwing up the parlour window,
and loudly seconding the invitation.
Mrs. Philips was always glad to see her nieces; and the two eldest, from their recent absence,
were particularly welcome; and she was eagerly expressing her surprise at their sudden return
home, which, as their own carriage had not fetched them, she should have known nothing
about, if she had not happened to see Mr. Jones’s shopboy in the street, who had told
her that they were not to send any more draughts to Netherfield, because the Miss Bennets were
come away, when her civility was claimed towards Mr. Collins by Jane’s introduction of him.
She received him with her very best politeness, which he returned with as much more, apologizing
for his intrusion, without any previous acquaintance with her, which he could not help flattering
himself, however, might be justified by his relationship to the young ladies who introduced
him to her notice.
Mrs. Philips was quite awed by such an excess of good breeding; but her contemplation of
one stranger was soon put an end to by exclamations and inquiries about the other, of whom, however,
she could only tell her nieces what they already knew, that Mr. Denny had brought him from
London, and that he was to have a lieutenant’s commission in the ——shire.
She had been watching him the last hour, she said, as he walked up and down the street,—and
had Mr. Wickham appeared, Kitty and Lydia would certainly have continued the occupation;
but unluckily no one passed the windows now except a few of the officers, who, in comparison
with the stranger, were become “stupid, disagreeable fellows.”
Some of them were to dine with the Philipses the next day, and their aunt promised to make
her husband call on Mr. Wickham, and give him an invitation also, if the family from
Longbourn would come in the evening.
This was agreed to; and Mrs. Philips protested that they would have a nice comfortable noisy
game of lottery tickets, and a little bit of hot supper afterwards.
The prospect of such delights was very cheering, and they parted in mutual good spirits.
Mr. Collins repeated his apologies in quitting the room, and was assured, with unwearying
civility, that they were perfectly needless.
As they walked home, Elizabeth related to Jane what she had seen pass between the two
gentlemen; but though Jane would have defended either or both, had they appeared to be wrong,
she could no more explain such behaviour than her sister.
Mr. Collins on his return highly gratified Mrs. Bennet by admiring Mrs. Philips’s manners
and politeness.
He protested that, except Lady Catherine and her daughter, he had never seen a more elegant
woman; for she had not only received him with the utmost civility, but had even pointedly
included him in her invitation for the next evening, although utterly unknown to her before.
Something, he supposed, might be attributed to his connection with them, but yet he had
never met with so much attention in the whole course of his life.